hello and welcome it's active inference
guest stream number
42.1 on May 10 2023
we're here with Juan Diego Bogota and
Zach Jabara we're going to have a
presentation time Consciousness in
computational phenomenology a temporal
analysis of active inference by the
authors followed by a discussion so
thank you both very much for being here
we'll look forward to your presentation
and off to you
cool thank you so I should start out
right
brilliant so hello everybody my name is
I'm one of the co-authors of this paper
I'm a PhD student at the University of
Exeter in the UK and kind of my broad
interstar philosophical phenomenology
and how it can be related to empirical
sciences and more specifically to
cognitive science and to our
understanding of of Consciousness so
what we're going to do now is I'm going
to give a broad context or paper I'm
going to talk about the theoretical and
philosophical context that motivated our
paper and then zag will talk about kind
of the specifics of our analysis of
active imprints so let me start now
so to kind of situate ourselves in the
broader literature uh I guess there's a
big big cluster of discussions and
topics and approaches within cognitive
science and conscious and studies that
as it as its names
um so that's just trying to explain
Consciousness uh scientifically within
that kind of big category of approaches
there's a very specific set which is um
which is trying to connect philosophical
phenomenology with the Natural Sciences
so we may call this the Naturalization
of phenomenology I'll talk about all
these in a bit I just want to kind of
situate ourselves within the broader
context one of these approaches is quite
popular in some circles which is called
Neo phenomenology and was first
introduced or proposed by Francisco
arella in the late 90s but recently
varela's project has been kind of
elaborated on by people within the fep
and active nurse community and and
they're talking about what it's called
computational neural phenomenology or
computational phenomenology which as
we'll see tries to connect the original
project of neurofenaminology of bringing
together cognitive science and
management but it gives an active
inference twist to this whole story
and this is where our project is
situated uh our main purpose in the
paper is to was to give a temporal
analysis of the structure of active
inference and in a bit I'll explain you
why we thought this was important
so uh as you probably know uh
Consciousness is a bit of a difficult
phenomenon to explain explain
scientifically uh we have nowadays a lot
of models and theories scientific
theories to try to address Consciousness
but there's always this kind of
lingering worry that there is a gap an
explanatory gap between our empirical
understanding of the old nature and
Consciousness because how we usually do
science is try to address and capture
empirical phenomena for a third person
perspective whereas Consciousness is
something that is allegedly given only
for a first person perspective so we're
on always experiencing the world from
our first person perspective and
allegedly we don't really have access to
to Consciousness as these empirical
phenomena we can see in the world
so that's kind of an epistemological gap
between How We Do Science and how we
understand Consciousness without doing
much science there's also the so hard
problem of Consciousness which is to say
that we don't really know how something
that Consciousness may arise from say
neobiological phenomena or empirical
phenomena more generally so this is kind
of a general context which shows that
Consciousness is quite difficult to
understand I don't think we would want
to say that it's impossible to you to
explain it from a scientific perspective
but it's it's somewhat difficult
in the broader context of conscious and
studies uh since the early 90s there's
been some proposals within cognitive
scientists of cognitive science and
philosophy of mind is trying to connect
this whole idea of explaining
Consciousness scientifically with what
it's known within philosophy as
phenomenology so importantly here when
we talk about phenomenology we're using
a very specific and technical term so in
the literature you may distinguish two
different ways of talking about
phenomenology there's the usual broader
sense in which we may mean kind of the
what it's like to experience something
or the qualitative contents of of
experience this is not what we're
talking about here
rather we're referring to phenomenology
which is very specific philosophical
tradition which was first proposed by
Edward Jose in the early 20th century
and was poorly developed by people like
Marcus melopenti Martin Heidegger Simon
De vavois and there's a long long
tradition going on there and what's
interesting about phenomenology is that
it's simply a philosophical method and
way of studying the invariant structures
of Consciousness so what all these
phenomenologists are trying to say is to
capture what they call the essential uh
kind of characteristics of what it's
like to be conscious of the our lived
experience through which we experience
the world
we do this by describing and analyzing
precisely these experiences and you may
think that this is pretty much what uh
kind of the broader sense of phenomenal
is trying to to get to through this idea
of like what the what it's like to
experience something but actually
phenomenologists are not really
interested in the word of experience
they're not really interested in the
context of of Consciousness so when
abnormal is talking about say perceptual
experience they're not really interested
in the redness of the red or you know
the flavor of an apple this kind of what
what philosophers or qualia rather
they're actually interesting how is it
possible that these experiences come to
be so this is how it's this refers to
these structures when we talk about for
example the the temporal structure of
Consciousness when we talk about
activity embodiment
but the important thing here is that
we're focusing on the how we experience
not what we experience and that's very
important because at least how I see it
I don't know about Zac uh this town
actually constrains the what so it's
very different to imagine uh an apple
than to experience it so there's a
difference between the how we're
experiencing the world and and that
constrains uh the specific contents of
our experience and this is important for
the broader context of explaining
conscious scientifically because
arguably if we're focusing on how we're
trying to to capture the essentials of
Consciousness and this is a project that
was one of the kind of this project was
spearheaded by Francisco arellia in the
in the 90s but we can actually Trace
back this idea to the works of merlot on
T and Adam Griffith in the philosophical
tradition we can also talk about
um Uber drivers and more recently
there's a kind of a very broad uh
discussion about whether and how can we
connect these philosophical
considerations with scientific
perspectives of consciousness
and this brings me to the so-called
project of the Naturalization of
phenomenal
we do science
into your world through the land of the
natural course we have
people understanding of the world
instead of metaphysical and
epistemological commitments such as that
there's a material world out there
which isn't get to know through some
addicts or doing empirical tests that's
that's how we finds very broadly
speaking but when you go and look the
literature the phenomenological
literature what phenomenologists provide
are not causal explanations of
Consciousness they are simply describing
a set of what they call motivational
connections which not really
um identify with causality which is the
the main thing that science is trying to
capture causal relationships also
there's a issue that phenomenality is
not positing empirical entities so when
we talk about say unconsciousness we're
not talking about empirical thing and
empirical object arguably we're talking
about a set of processes which and this
is kind of the shift from from the
scientific issues to those possible ones
we're talking about something that is
arguably prior to to objectivity so
phenomenologists are often reminding the
readers
that before we're doing science like
we're doing theoretical science we're
experiencing the world and we're
therefore because it's something that is
prior epistemologically to science and
to try to capture uh Consciousness
scientifically almost to uh commit a
category mistake
um so given these worries the question
is whether we can actually link
phenomenology with empirical science
such as cognitive science and this
question is precisely what we talk about
what we call the so-called project of
naturalization of phenomenology which is
to mean uh how are we to to mate to make
phenomenology continuous with empirical
science there's a lot of proposals in
the literature there's a a very
important book published in 1999 edited
by jean-petitor called naturalizing
phenomenology which the editors and
several authors discuss how and whether
we can actually naturalize phenomenology
but one of the most famous proportions
is precisely uh Francisco varela's
proposal of the Naturalization
epidemiology which is called neural
phenomenology
so put very simply what neuro
phenomenology is all about is to provide
a non-reductive approach to the study of
Consciousness this non-reductive
approach takes seriously both the
analysis and descriptions made by
phenomenologists as well as the
scientific understanding we have of the
neurobiology that
um underpins our lived experience
these two kind of domains are put in
relation to one another by means of what
parallel called reciprocal constraints
so the idea is that a phenomenology can
constrain our understanding of the
neurobiological underpinnings and these
neural biological underpinnings can also
constrain our understanding of
experience or phenomenological
understanding of experience
interestingly and this is where kind of
the computational and mathematical
aspect comes in Varela also suggested
that in order to to achieve this kind of
circulation between phenomenology and
empirical science we have to have some
sort of bridge or what it calls a
generative passage that allows us to go
from these very abstract
phenomenological descriptions of
experience to the more concrete somatic
and the concrete descriptions of somatic
and neural processes that underpin lived
experience and this very abstract level
that allows for this uh passage for this
bridge and for him for valea was the use
of dynamical systems theory and more
specifically models of non-linear
Dynamics
so if you look at his 99 paper on time
Consciousness what he does is to connect
Edmonton Hospital's analysis of
temporality with certain neural
processes by introducing dynamical
models into the picture this is what
phenomena neuro phenomenology is all
about
but more recently and uh inspired by
this whole project of new phenomenology
Maxwell Randstad and colleagues have
proposed to further elaborate on this
project by employing generative modeling
techniques such as active inputs to
provide this passage between
phenomenology and and the neurobiology
and what is interesting about it is that
if you do so introduce genetic modeling
techniques what you get is the idea that
these have experienced how experienced
the world or what phenomenal is called
Constitution can be modeled or described
in terms of patient inference or
approximate basic Librarians an
important bit here is that there's a
different different ways of interpreting
this one way would be to say that
Constitution or how experienced the
world's literally
a matter of basic inference or there's a
more kind of instrumentalist or
non-realistic conception of this product
which would say we can actually just
model or describe our lived experience
and how experience World in terms of
approximated patient inference in this
context what happens is that what the
the Hat the what what experience in the
world is constituted through a set of
inferences which are informed by
likelihood mappings and you know all
these materials that come in place into
generative modeling
so this kind of a broader context uh
that informs our proposal but you may
ask why we were focusing on time
Consciousness and I think Zach is one's
going to say something about this but
for now what I just want to say that
there's good reasons both
phenomenological reasons and scientific
reasons to to
apply uh these kind of models to time
conscious on the one hand and
importantly time Consciousness is simply
what we mean by time Consciousness our
experience of time so how we
subjectively experience the passage of
time
and this this phenomenon Consciousness
enjoys a sort of privileged position
within uh philosophical phenomenological
literature for example who's real
heidiagram and leban tea are some
prominent phenomenologists who take time
conscious to be the most basic structure
of Consciousness the point is that all
that we're experiencing all the time is
always experiencing experienced in time
there's always this kind of temporal
flow to the way we experience the world
and this is kind of uh essential to the
way we we engage with the world so if
this is the most basic structure of
Consciousness and we're trying to
understand Consciousness scientifically
by modeling through say genetic models
or or dynamical System Theory models
then probably uh we should start by the
most basic level time Consciousness and
this is something that several authors
have actually tried to do so there's for
example both bang elders and barelas
dynamical models of time Consciousness
which borrow from Edmund husse uh
phenomenological analysis there's also
gracious computational model of the same
processes more recently there's varnia
basis a predictive processing model of
time Consciousness so if you see there's
also a relatively long tradition of
trying to capture the Dynamics of time
Consciousness in terms of mathematical
modeling so now moving on to to our
table analysis our main question is
whether actually active inference is
capable of modeling these Dynamics in a
way that is um that is that makes
Justice to the original phenomenological
analysis made out by Post Road and
that's it for me now I'll give the the
floor to Zach
here I am and I hope you can hear me and
see me
yep thanks
I'm gonna share my screen
all right so I'm gonna pick up here from
where uh
left
um I basically
like you said we basically we started
talking about well there is this problem
right
um with the flow of experience and
um this discreetness in which we we
model
um well whatever phenomena really
especially in cognitive science
um so there is this relationship and
this claim that we are in fact modeling
features of Human Experience like
perception memory and so on but it's
very few if any of them really take
seriously the flow of of Human
Experience
um so phenomenology is is for
philosophers uh and not for scientists
apparently so computational
phenomenology like JD just talked about
is like this new subfield
um that takes both seriously the
computational approaches but also
phenomenology and it's trying to sort of
find this middle ground in which we can
have a conversation and of course big
kudos to to Maxwell for this fantastic
Milestone I should I should say before I
start that I'm very happy that JD's Juan
Diego is here
because I think that there is a lot of
thoughts and and he has this very
cautious way of thinking and
basically formulating his sentences that
I do not uh have
um so it's good that he's here and I
should I should probably also say
explicitly that I'm I will not be
speaking for his behalf at all but we
agree on basically all of this
so just to be short
all right so before I uh dive into the
whole
temporality and active inference aspect
of of
um of our paper I would like I would
just like to start with a small exotic
experiment and I usually give this to to
those who don't understand why I
personally think in time all the time
so uh let's imagine that we have to
understand our own experience of of
space b this is the space b this is the
space a it's a space c so these are all
very very different spaces right and
imagine there's two like a parallel
universe in the first Universe in the
first scenario you approach space b from
space a right so this is you and you're
basically moving in this direction and
you're experiencing this space now in
Another Universe right
could be the fictional you're in this
person
you're this person and you're
approaching space b now I usually ask my
students do you think that this
experience of space b will be the same
and usually they all go like well uh by
far the majority says no
um it's it's two very very different
experiences and they have nothing to do
with each other and this is basically
what I am what I'm what I'm sort of
asking people to sort of start thinking
about there is no one-to-one isometric
relationship between space and
experience
and I think this is a very very
important and very I wouldn't say
obvious but to me it's very clear that
they cannot be like that it cannot be
that one space or one specific type of
content will make me experience the
content the same way every time
and I think that the reason for that is
change right time Dynamics Everything
Changes this is sort of uh what brings
me into this will bring us into the
discussion about
substance philosophy and process
philosophy I will not unfold that at all
but I will mention a few from time to
time a few things about them so here I'm
just going trying to make the point that
even like intuitively which is usually
what we go what we like but we reason
with these thought experiments that's
basically why they're here and it just
appears to us that space is not
necessarily uh directly mapped to an
experience
because we have to consider time right
so I'm asking three questions here and
the first one will be how does the
continuous flow in Human Experience
emerge and I will try to answer that
through the differences and similarities
between what we call objective and
subjective time I will elaborate on that
and then I will try to answer how we can
we extract principles from personally
and temporality so Edmond Russell that
that uh Juan Diego just talked about
and to answer that I will talk a bit
about the enduring present and the
integration of two types of
temporalities that's the objective and
subjective one and then finally what
structural answer does active inference
comply with these principles sort of you
know using phenomenology to come up with
a principle constraints and see whether
active inference is sort of playing by
those rules or not and for that I will
try to give you our temporal analysis of
active inference as a partially
observable Markov decision process a
computational model so a pump DP
so first things first objective and
subject this time so the objective time
what do we mean by this and I I like to
think of them
um as as roughly
um what corresponds to substance and
process philosophy respectively right
because object uh objective time sort of
it deals with uh spatial features and
everything that is rooted in the space
whereas subjective time I like to think
has more to do with how things change
um so to give an example and a substance
philosopher would say that the sun is
simply the sun it's a thing and it's a
sun whereas a process philosopher would
say that no it's a burning Planet it's
doing something and so the river is not
just a river it's running water and you
are not you you're always changing and
so on it's heraklitis this is basically
the idea and the difference between
substance and process velocity now if we
project this idea like this abstract
idea onto onto the discussion on the
relationship and between objective and
subject to time
um
we might we we first of all it's an
important discussion because
computational models operate on
computers and these follow the laws of
physics right so we are sort of Bound By
by the laws of physics and we sort of
have to talk about objective time in in
the context of the laws of physics so
um I like to think that in space we can
have several units at the same time
right like you can you can count
different kinds of sheep like they don't
even have to look alike or anything like
I know that the farmers can tell the
difference between the animals but maybe
to someone who cannot it will just be
like a sheep one sheep two sheep three
and so on and you can then even say a
number like you can go let's take a
sheep number five and you will not even
imply any other ship from from well one
to four you don't imply them at all you
just mean this one right there's an
identity versus a similarity uh
discussion that needs to be taken up
there so space allows us to sort of
categorize and discretize the world and
I like to think about this as the way
that geometric Sim sort of functions
where we can take space and just divide
it infinitely
right you can always take something like
anything and you can split it in two
then in two again then in two again and
you essentially you essentially get what
they call the geometric series which is
um interestingly how you approach
continuous numbers and continuous
functions anyway uh of course I mean
this uh in in theoretical terms because
at some point we're going to reach the
plank length length and then we're gonna
have to deal with a different kind of
problem but in any case my point here is
that space allows us in the first place
to think in degrees right like if
there's a change in degree how much
something is
but time I think operates in a different
way
Sam sort of has this single unit right
um it's just a single kind as opposed to
the degrees so there's a difference in
kind when we change moments not a change
in degrees which will have in space so
there cannot be any division of time
this is why I usually say that time for
me is completely indivisible it doesn't
make sense to to compare two different
moments because they have two different
units and we cannot compare them
so when I say that we measure time
um
I'm basically saying that whenever you
measure any time you measure it the same
way so when I say five seconds I imply
all the seconds between zero and five as
opposed to to the space with the Sheep
so I guess you can also think about the
units
um
of time I'm talking about the measure of
time I think that sort of makes it
easier to understand
but because these computational models
they're basically operating with
computers that are operating uh with
electricity and basically the laws of
physics
um I think it's important here to to
sort of think about that in a broader
term
um and I wanted to briefly quote uh Sir
Arthur Eddington who sort of is famous
for introducing the idea of the arrow of
time stating that so far as physics is
concerned times arrow is a property of
entropy alone but I think that there's
some truth to that
um so if we consider the whole universe
as a closed system right then we would
expect the Heat and the energy to at
some point even out completely
thermodynamically speaking right is the
is the thermodynamic equilibrium and
this is where the entropy is is highest
um so because the entropy of the system
is maximized or
um basically it's it's at its highest
value it has reached a state where all
the possible ways of Distributing energy
uh between the the particles has been
completely exhausted like there's no
reason for any particle to move anymore
there is no harm cold everything is the
same temperature it's the maximum of of
uh entropy so
um well I guess this is also why you you
sort of say that energy is unavailable
to perform any work right so
um probably I should also mention here
that entropy actually is a Greek word
for transformation and change and I
think this is exactly why uh it fits
very well with my understanding of time
here uh is to change right it's the
process
so entropy in a in a abstract way I
think it sort of tries to explain not
only uh spatial States but also visual
stage in relation to time like how they
can how they can uh change so uh
thermodynamically speaking there will
always be a transfer from hot to cold in
order to reach maximum entropy to sort
of create a balance and uh importantly
there is a linear causal relationship
right there's always like one damn thing
after the other as the saying goes uh
there's never anything other than like
the linear way
and it goes like the past causes the
future and so on and of course this is
no consensus about this lots of people
in quantum physics and quantum mechanics
will completely oppose that and think
that it actually goes the other way
around but typically when we talk about
this
um at least I believe in Newtonian
physics there is a linear cause of
relationship so the features of
objective time is that it's spatial and
that it's temporarily linear
now let's move on to the subjective time
and as Juan Diego already said it's the
ABCs of of uh well it's the a in the
ABCs of Consciousness and subjectivity
so uh it's going to give a a brief
demonstration of how this particular
diagram which was developed originally
by idmod husal in his uh basically
um
we have to think about the black line
here as the objective time sort of right
uh one event second event third and
fourth and so on and basically if we
just take the present here as being the
the event B well there is some kind of
expectation of what's going to happen at
the next moment that is affecting this
movement here but not only that there is
also another layer to that is going sort
of a what we call a pro tension right a
protection of what's going to happen
even Beyond C and you can actually draw
this huge diagram out there and you will
eventually get like a kind of protection
about the future
but at the same time we also have some
information about retention right
there's something that happened already
that we're sort of uh building our
present moment based on our retention
so the retention sort of explains the
immediate past and we do not refer to
this as memory or working memory it's
very explicit that it's not the same
thing
um I guess the one way we can think
about this is also in in terms of
memories uh in terms of Melodies is what
I'm trying to say uh and sentences so
for example my sentence right now I
started it a few moments ago but it's
still going and you still have the full
sentence in your head and so on and so
on
um and basically when we talk about the
structure of of human
experience and I think that uh Juan
Diego's absolutely right when he says
that for any naturalization
naturalization project for it to succeed
it must at the very least get the temple
or the right I think this is like the
basics of the basics
so
in this case the way that Edmonton
thinks about it is that he he thinks
about it as the the living present being
made of of a synthesis of retention and
protection and this is what we call the
Primal impression it's the present
moment that will not refer to it always
as the Primal impression but that is I
believe what do you what you call in in
philosophy the technical term for for
living prison
but the the main issue here Still
Remains right so how can it's what I'm
writing here how can a sequential
structure of time be compatible with one
that appears to flow like this is this
is the the the the the the the the the
the issue that we are dealing with here
um and I think that there is uh two very
important principles that we can point
out from here resilient synthesis that
any experienced Moment In Time cannot
consist of a discrete now moment alone
but must instead coexist with the
immediate past and immediate future
which is basically the retention and the
pro tension in this case but there's
also a very bergsonian aspect to this
which is the interpenetration right so
the present moment requires the coming
together of subjective and objective
temporal structures which is exactly
also what you see here there's an
objective direction of of uh of time but
it's constituted by well past and future
all the time
and this is basically
um if you look at it in in diagrammatic
uh or graphical way well the objective
time that we call the spatial and linear
cause relationship we said that one
event causes the next one causes the
next one causes the next one and so on
the the arrow is very very clear but in
subjective time we sort of have this um
let's say opportunity to well flip one
of the Arabs and say that well if I'm
looking at the event B not a and C but
just the event B well the event B is
constituted by a retention and a
protection so we have sort of flipped
the arrow here and this sort of
um these are two very different orders
of time as we call them in our paper and
one is characterized by its
unidirectional development in time which
is the objective one the other one is
characterized by bi-directional
development in time and this is the
subjective one basically what we do
um oh probably I should mention here
that the notation here is very important
to to sort of get that we're always
using the superscript for the objective
and the subscript for the the for the
subject I meant objective obviously the
super superscript for objective and
subscript but subjective
um time dimensions and usually we use T
for the superscript and Tau for the
subscript just to be sure so what we
propose in our paper is basically this
integrated continuity where we try to
combine both of them into Australian
interpretation and obviously we're also
relying here a lot on on on
um uh conditional dependencies here and
this is from statistics
um I guess this is also why I I
personally like to think of this as a
kind of a tribute to Boltzmann's
statistical approach to entropy right
because he was the one who sort of took
that step away from from uh uh simply
thermodynamics and movement in between
energy to thinking about it more as uh
statistics and probability uh
distributions and I think that was very
fascinating I think in many ways this is
kind of a tribute to that right so
taking way of thinking of it and sort of
adding this conditional dependency layer
to the development of time
um
so um
right this is this is what we've sort of
uh get at right so if you look at the
present moment B this is the event that
we're trying to understand well there's
a B minus one uh in in in in the
objective time but it's actually a pro
tension so it's actually a plus one as
well because it was a plus one
retention later but for the next event
which is C and you can actually
generalize this uh the way we do at Each
corner here so why uh what the sub uh
the superscript the object of time plus
minus K and the subject of time plus
minus 10 and you can do the same for for
the other way
um the other direction
so
um
basically what we've been talking about
so far is is
um talking about systems and whether
they're how they function and especially
I talked about the universe functioning
as kind of a closed system I think
that's a huge assumption and I'm not
really buying into all of this but it's
basically a good way to to explain uh
the approaches that we have made
but the body open it functions as an
open system because it's exchanging
energy and information all the time and
I'm preaching to the choir here you all
know about Market blankets and I don't
think that it's important to sort of
introduce it to this forum and but I
would like to just pinpoint a few things
the first one is that I want to remind
you that active inference assumes that
there's a border between the central
nervous system and and the environment
and that can be identified through a
markup blanket and I also would like to
emphasize the fact that it's describing
the processes and Dynamics rather than
the things themselves and I'm really
emphasizing the process versus The Thing
and
oh okay I'm all right so basically
Market blankets they represent the
statistical boundaries right
um based on on these conditional
conditional relationships and they're
typically applied in the spatial domain
this is my point uh it's it's a
statistical boundary in the spatial
domain
um also I should probably mention that
when I talk about conditional
dependencies because I realized that
there has been uh quite a lot of debate
about what we mean when we talk about
from the conditional dependencies uh
well not specifically for our paper but
in general in the statistical work
um what we mean here is that there is a
relationship between two or more events
that that are dependent
when a third event occurs this is
basically the most generic uh definition
of of the conditional dependencies which
you can find in in a Judea Pearl's work
on Markov and Beijing Networks
so my point here was just to say that
for the markup blanket you see that
um it's just a statistical boundary and
I know that Carl's monograph the famous
monograph sort of takes that one step
further and suggests that well there are
a markup blankets actually make up the
physical and the spatial boundary
between things
um whereas the way that we apply this is
still in terms of statistics and
Dynamics and processes so we don't
really deal with with that aspect here
so
um
should we really expect things this is
my point here this is the question that
I'm asking should we really expect
things in active inference which is a
process Theory I mean I understand that
the spatial boundaries they are a matter
of convenience but can we really expect
them to sort of you know divide what
what really is like the central nervous
system when does it really transfer into
B into uh uh into the actual uh flesh of
the body
and these spatial transitions they sort
of happen in degree and if we look at
the borderline we will we will be
looking at that forever and ever and we
look at neurons and then atoms of
neurons and so on and so on we will
never be able to really find the
delineation this is where I think that
the idea of temporal Marco blankets sort
of is is a good idea just to briefly sum
this up right so Mark of blankets is of
this particular node
um is constituted by its parents and its
kids and the kids of of the parents of
the kids here so anything that is around
that will not hold any valuable
information about this particular node
again I'm probably preaching to the
choir here
um but here I'm basically asking so
um
the delineation is is smart because it
it's sort of you know it
um it gives us tractability right it
makes it tractable we can start thinking
about the Dynamics between things
um but in the context of time
we might ask can we apply the mark of
blankets to the temporal structure
because we already drew them as
conditional dependencies so we we sort
of asked in our paper what are the
statistical boundaries of the present
moment so you I just show you this one
here before
um of the integrated continuity drawn up
here as a a network of conditional
dependencies so if I were to sort of
look at this particular Point uh the um
the the event B
well we will find that if we try to map
out this Markov blanket we will find
that well the information necessary to
understand this particular node is
actually constituted uh by by
um
a bit of the present and sorry a bit of
the past in a bit of the future right so
basically we're kind of cheeky doing
this when I think about it because we're
sort of dressing the structure with a
blanket that that um that happens in
time and I think that
um
obviously the the
uh how can I put this this is
unconventional and which means that this
will have to be
um there will have to be some
limitations uh compared to the the
conventional way you would you would use
markup blankets in spatial conditions uh
special uh relationships
so
um first we find that well all the
information needed to understand the
present moment
um well we find them to comply
completely with uh both principles of of
phenomology we basically get the
interpenetration of Passenger and the
Pres on the future and we also get this
integration between the objective and
the subjective time so we get an
integration in this direction and we get
an integration in this direction here
um so
that was actually our very first
surprise so the second surprise when we
did this it sort of occurred when we try
to understand to understand
um what does it take to update the
present moment right and to actually
propagate the whole model through time
and for that we need to analyze the
update function of a standard active
inference
pmdp so
um
yeah probably I should mention that the
conventional pmdps in robotics they
don't use the same kind of of update
function as we use it in in active
inference and because they're much more
explicit about the reward functions and
so on and active inference uh obviously
caches all of that out as a free energy
minimization so anyway the Dynamics of
the present moment are constituted by
two potentials we have them up here and
a single retention which is down here
and basically you will be able to get
this particular equation and once we
start to sort of
um because these are factors so if you
if we if we sort of want to turn that
into sums we need to convert them to the
logarithms instead and basically if we
just keep this one in mind and put it
over here we see that the first line is
our derived model from the slide before
and of course like any anyone who's
modeling we have to engage with this
very Central exercise which I like to
think about as providing quality to
quantity and I think this is a very very
particular problem that the
researchers in the field of
computational phenomenology have to deal
with as well
so keeping this exercise in mind because
I will I will have some comments about
this towards the end
um
so we have the hidden protection at t
plus one and the hidden Primal
impression at T and T plus one basically
what you see here
um and then we have the observed
retention at T minus one this is
basically what we derived from from our
uh model from before now uh the second
line here is basically the update
function of of the active influence from
DP and once we actually just strip it
away if uh strip it from all its uh
action policies you noticed here there
are no action policies in this update uh
I will return to why we did that then
basically what you have is the well it's
pretty straightforward actually you have
the prior which is the forward message
passing and you have the predictive
which is the backward one and you have
the likely outcome
um
so
our notation here with the double
timeline the Double Dimension of time in
the single notation sort of allows us to
understand better what is actually going
on here if we map
um the phonological version or equation
that we derived onto the existing update
function and
so I've omitted here a few equations
that if you're interested you can find
them all in the paper but essentially
once it's all mapped out it appears as
if the update function can be translated
into kind of a prior protection a
predictive Primal impression and a
likely retention so very similar to how
protection was brought backward the
retention here is brought forward in
time linked with the likelihood and the
and the hidden state
so
um the discovery or a surprise as you
rather say is both that the model
appealed to the same temporal structure
as the the active inference model
although in a different way
so I just took this
um
quote from uh from our paper because
this is how we sort of reason about it
but this gives rise to an integrated
structure of time where the past depends
on prior predictions and the future of
of my likely retention which speaks to
different logical understanding of
experience so just as in the hostility
analysis the retention Primal impression
and protection jointly make up the
living present then we refer to uh the
set of inferences presented here as the
living inferences which is sort of you
know a work like here between between
formalities so since they are drawn this
they serve together uh sorry since
jointly they serve to describe within an
active inference model the phenological
process that gave rise to the living
present
so this is basically uh me working my
way here to to the end
um we don't have the answer here um I
still think that this is very clear here
but we have a suggestion for an answer
which is the continuity that we
experience is due to the
interpenetration and synthesis of an
objective and subjective temporal
dimension so yes
um can we extract principles that was
basically our answer here how does the
continue flow in Human Experience emerge
well through the penetration and
synthesis
um of two temporal Dimensions can we
extract principles from her shoulder and
temporality yes we can easily extract
principles from houstonology we just
need to note on the what conditions this
is done and I think this is an important
note because you remember when I said
that there's this quality to quantity
exercise that we all have to engage in
so basically my view is that
computational phenomenology if it wants
to contribute to science this would be
an extremely important exercise but when
and how quality is attributed to a
specific quantity it needs to be
extensively and like very very clearly
uh like elaborated argumentation because
um so you can ask why does this
particular parameter here right
um like typically in active interest
that would be the temperature you say
that oh this this particular parameters
it represents attention well does it
behave like attention and to what extent
because it will have a limit and we just
need to know when is that limit
um basically in our case we saw that the
temporality can be modeled but we need
to know under what circumstances so in
our case we assume that the present
moment is not a static Frozen moment in
time just like space but it endures
there's a duration right and it's
essentially this Insight that allows us
to create such an integration between
the two temporal dimensions so finally
um
I'd like to think that we we
demonstrated the potential of active
inference in being used as a as a Point
of Departure to model basically the flow
of subjective experience
um but I think that we have yet to begin
analyzing anything beyond that
um we basically need to start thinking
about including action policies so
that's motion and action and of course
essentially we would arrive at something
that looks like content right
um so so I guess this is in a way our
rigorous approach and and humble uh uh
start with with will the very Basics
um and I think that this very slow
approach is is exactly how it should be
because we should be cautious
um about this relationship between
phenomenology and computational modeling
just a few words here about our future
work and what we were working on now and
this is
um
um actually
um this is an example of of
um one of the things that we are working
on I will say that right now we are
focusing on another
um uh perspective of our work which has
to do with the direct integration of
motor intentionality and an action but
basically in this particular project
we're sort of trying to map out the
exact
um let's say structure of of time in any
computational model right because we
when you analyze the update function of
any computational model it will reveal
its temporal structure like how does it
bring the past into the future right
into this propagation time
um so you we could ask like what about
the CNN's right uh convolutional new
networks what about recurrent neural
networks or Auto encoders or all the
other kinds of algorithms how do they
function like how do they update their
function and I think that
um by analyzing all of these different
algorithms and their update function we
could sort of map out all of these
temporal structures and understand
better how they are propagating in in
in in space Through Time
so um this would be I think my uh my
last slide here yes thank you for your
attention
that was much longer than I am sorry
about that
was I muted the whole time
longer in time or what exactly do you
mean by that
well I would say subjective the time was
very short uh
objective time was much better
thank you both for this really
excellent excellent dyad of
presentations and I will uh
pass first to Dean or Ali whoever would
like to just jump in with a first
thought or reflection please feel free
go ahead Ali
uh well thank you so much for your
amazing presentation
uh gosh I have so many comments and
questions to ask
um I don't know where to begin but
um
you see because I'm also deeply
interested in um process philosophy as
well and if not necessarily a
whiteheadian process philosophy but
generally thinking in terms of flows and
flux and so on as opposed to
substance and stasis uh but uh in my
view uh well
historian phenomenology uh first the
these conceptions the flows and
the temporality and retention protection
and so on uh is a step toward uh kind of
process thinking right but
ultimately uh I believe that certainly
on philosophy or more precisely
historian phenomenology uh fails to
escape the uh the Trap of substance
thinking uh because uh you see uh if I
read a direct code from the hussarel
himself he says that time is like a flow
but with divisions in other words not
like a flow at all and in fact the
opposite of the flow
so uh the reason he's he doesn't bestow
uh the kind of this kind of Primacy to
the temporality or continuity is because
obviously it results in a contradiction
in other words uh if I mean as if what
constitutes objects um
uh if time is what constitutes objects
in time obviously that cannot itself be
an object in time so uh he needs a more
primary uh way to or more primary
concept to account for uh that kind of
division in temporality uh namely the
absolute flu uh but uh well there are
some arguments regarding uh whether we
can escape this uh apparent or real uh
contradiction or not uh which I'm not
going into detail but at one point I
wanted to make is that if we uh also try
to bestow this kind of Primacy to the
absolute flow or who's certainly an
absolute flu don't you think we
basically contradict our initial aim to
escape that
um
kind of um I mean substance thinking
given this uh contradiction that arises
that's one of my question uh the other
ones
um is about
um the conception of objective time and
subjective time uh so uh interestingly
well who saw you you also began your
discussion of Australian phenomenology
with
um musical crystals famous musical
examples
and it's very interesting that probably
the most influential music theory of the
past hundred years uh namely the
shankarian theory uh it is fundamentally
a phenomenological Theory because uh he
tries to theorize how we perceive each
moment in music as a culmination of
every bits of Music we've heard so far
until
that point and on the other hand the
anticipation of what is to come
and the others so each point of music is
a kind of combination of all the
elements of retention
um Primal
Primal Primal moment and also the
pretension but
um
there are some criticisms put forward
especially uh by Gerald Levinson
regarding
the feasibility of this kind of
description uh because of our limited
capacity of our short-term and working
memory in trying to at least consciously
grasp all of the details of the past and
also our limited capacity to predict
every
um a possible future or every every
anticipation from that single point uh
so my question is uh and also uh there
is another criticism regarding the uh
the ignoring
the uh per elasticity of perceived time
in shankarian uh Theory and also in his
early and phenomenology so my question
is how would you account
for this kind of apparent elasticity
that all of us experience in
um the subjective or manifest time
and my very last question sorry it took
me so long and my very last question
about the is about the objective time
which is do you have any particular
justification or any particular reason
for choosing one among many of the
physical theories of objective time so
for instance we have uh view from
quantum gravity review from relativity
which basically are seeing can be seen
as kind of contradictory because in
general relativity uh we we allow for
the time for temporality to be
fundamental but in quantum gravity
temporality is a kind of emergent
property that emerges from uh to each
wheeler equation so uh is there a
specific reason that you
you chose you decided to choose Carlo
ravelli's uh I mean conception of
objective time uh again apologies for my
long-winded questions
I'm looking forward
probably a little bit better
so we can see each other when you start
the when I think some of the first
questions were about the about the
phonology or I can actually I have a few
comments to that and I think that if I
may uh
um yeah go ahead go ahead
um
I'll talk some comments but go ahead
yeah so I would like to just start by
making this the the distinction between
um time perception and the temporality
and phenomenology
um because
um temporality is more basic than
um time perception time perception is
actually a skill it's actually uh
something like it's it's sort of like
attention and memory and so on it's a
skill set we have and it's something
that we are performing uh some are good
at it uh some are very bad like me
um but in any case temporality in
phenomenology it talks not about how you
um your skills about time perception
it's more about the actual unfolding of
anything like any experience whatsoever
like me now shaping these thoughts to
sort of convey them I'm not thinking
about time perception I'm actually it's
happening and there's like this
unfolding of time constantly this
continuous flow right uh I have whenever
I talk about it I like to think about
Lee smallen's reality of time uh I think
that there is some truth to to to his
way of reasoning about time the fact
that it's real and it's actually more
real than space and space is actually
the emergent property of time that's
actually by the way from from uh
category Theory and geometry Theory as
well
um that's where where that comes from
but
um
because if you think about it like that
right if you think about the time being
the thing that sort of pushes us forward
right there's like this action this I
would I wouldn't even say this in
involuntary uh action like you're
constantly doing this it's constantly
happening so for me I would make a clear
distinction between time perception and
temporality now if I just jump directly
to the end of the question because
um I I love to deal with with the you
ask why did we go with color rovery's
thermodynamic Arrow of time
um there's a good reason for that
because in the beginning
um I believe we discussed briefly the uh
whether the divided equations because in
that equation you completely take away
time right you just say well basically
you can explain any kind of Dynamics and
and change without any variable of time
you just need special uh parameters
um I personally think that that's uh
great that shows that math Works uh
doesn't mean that that's how it works
um to me the way that I think about it
is is more about
um so uh it doesn't matter what I think
about why do we go with the
thermodynamic uh color of English
thermodynamic approach because he starts
with entropy and that sort of builds in
uh perfectly well on on our approach and
our analysis of active influence being
built on on entropy being however
another kind of entropy it still Builds
on the very same let's say ontology
right it's built on the same idea and it
fits that idea
um could still be wrong in any case if
you go with David and Wheeler's
equations you still have a another
dimension of time that is different from
the subjective one and I think I should
be clear here that I'm not saying that
um they exist independently I'm just
saying that it's two different things
and we can think about them individually
and there is an advantage in doing
something like that because then you can
start looking at how they integrate
afterwards so this is merely convenience
right
um there is no such thing as only a
subjective time without objective time
and the other way around this is not
part of of the paper it's a Way Beyond
the scope of the paper anyway
yeah kind of lashing into to Zach's
comment towards the end is that
when we were writing the paper we're
discussing slightly about how we should
address objective time and in the end we
decided to use catalog about this
framework as such as just a matter of
convenience I think at least I'm very
much instrumentalist in that sense that
you can have a lot of different stories
of how physical time works and that's
important and that's okay but in the end
I don't think that affects too much our
overall purpose which is to say there's
an integration between an objective
sense of time take color really take
quantum physics
Etc and subjectivity which in which we
are pretty much committed to the hotel
in framework which this brings me to the
other two questions
concerning the first one about uh kind
of the relationship between process
intology and reselling phenomenology I
think the important thing to note here
and this is my interpretation to be
honest is that when we talk about
Consciousness and time Consciousness and
the absolute flow within the consolidian
framework it's important to notice that
it is not a thing and I think it's also
an important thing to keep in mind when
we address how are we to explain
Consciousness scientifically it's uh I
do believe that's a sort of implicit
assumption within a lot of the
literature especially the earlier one
it's assumed that Consciousness insofar
is a phenomenon it's also a thing that
has to arise from say neural processes
or neophysiological process or whatever
kind of frame you're subscribing to but
it's not really that and that's the nice
thing about phenomenal this especially
in phenomenology is that when you go to
the kind of the deep level of whatever
is happening subjectively you won't find
a thing you find what he calls the
absolute flow which does sound like a
thing as a river and he does say that
it's it's a flow but it's not there's
always this hesitation the literature
because he he
notice that every inflow what we
experience there's always this uh
there's a lot of stuff happening at the
same time and in time but it kind of
keeps a structure which is retention
Primal impression and protection so
there's this this kind of paradoxical
nature to the absolute flow it's Pure
Flow but it has a specific structure but
when you look at how that structure
functions and that's kind of the the
step that he takes from what the
so-called static to the genetic or
dynamical phenomenology is that this
structure is just I said processes that
are always happening
not things it's it's not that retention
is a thing but in notes literally
process is happening synthesis as he
calls it and that's what we think it's
it's interesting to connect to the
active inference framework or any other
modeling framework is that then you
don't really have to capture a thing say
equality assay uh the redness of the red
but actually you're just trying to
capture processes with processes so you
have retention and you have inferences
that's it you don't have real things you
have to stop that is happening through
time and you don't really have to commit
to any sort of uh object ontology you
have just processes moving on through
which something more stable arises but
it's not a thing once again when we
experience say the bottle it's it's a
thing but it's always given itself in
time it's always changing I can see its
movement I can move around
all this time that's the nice thing
about it and concerning the other
question uh which was the one and uh the
limitations on uh okay working memory
about the elasticity of time perception
can you elaborate more about the the
concept of elasticity as you were using
it sure uh you see uh The Familiar
phenomena that we experience when we
somehow experience this speeding up or
slowing down uh the experience uh or
living present that's basically what I
mean by elasticity of time perception
I I
I often wondered because certainly when
we talk about subjective temporality in
the hotel incense that's not really what
he's trying to to capture that's quite
clear he's simply when he talks about
the structure of time conscience he is
very exploited we're talking about
formal structure that remains
ugly invariant through all experiences
but it's true that there's a sort of
flexibility to how to experience the the
world and this is literally a
speculation for me I have to sit down
and think more about it but I think
there's an important connection between
up activity and temporality here so
there's there's uh kind of uh especially
in activism there's this discussions
about how effectivity and time
Consciousness in the Australian or
phenomenal sense linked to one another
for example this is not an activism
Explorer Matthew Radcliffe talks about
styles of anticipation we may anticipate
something with anxiety or or with hope
or with fear and that probably stretches
out not only that we anticipate but how
we anticipate and that's that's very
important it seems to be how anticipate
something and what we're anticipating
something and it this also kind of
constitutes our general
um openness to the world because say I'm
sitting down completely bored waiting
for something not only the the
experience of time kind of straight
Islam sources out but also
you know there's a special kind of
effective atmosphere to our world but
once again this this kind of opens up
another question about for computational
neuropenemology which is okay now we
have inactive inference this kind of
clear-cut temporal a structure that
links up to cultural and phenomenology
how can we introduce effectivity into
the picture and there's of course a lot
of work and effectivity emotions at it
more generally in the active influence
framework but that's an interesting
question how can how does this relate to
our temporal model
I don't know if Sac has anything else to
add
I was just uh reminded of a few things
there uh I think you're you're totally
on point with with everything you said I
just want to emphasize the fact that the
stretch and the plasticity of time is
still in my opinion something of a skill
that we have right it's an impression
and that impression is something like
that we that we get at
um and just because I have that
experience doesn't mean uh if I had like
a twin and we were doing this not even
just a friend and we were doing the
exact same thing that stretch will be
very individual and it that just means
that it depends on well on who you are
and your skill at doing that I I cannot
really differentiate between time
perception and the plasticity that sort
of is implicit in time perception I
cannot distinguish that from like other
skills like being able to remember
something or directing your attention at
something
um because that's exactly the same thing
we don't have the same skill like some
people are very bad at suppressing a
peripheral information others are not
and it just continues like that
um but but I I do have a
um a point
um so do you guys know James Tyrell the
Light Designer uh artist American Artist
he's a fantastic Light Designer I highly
recommend you go see all of his work
um basically he has he studied the eye
and vision so never a vision he's not a
vision neuroscientist but he studied
vision for many many years and he's a
Light Designer and basically he creates
these huge installations everywhere
um and one that really caught my
attention was in Japan uh I think now
it's seven years ago where we went into
this pitch dark room right it's a big
Temple that was uh reconstructed pitch
dark couldn't see anything and you just
had to touch the wall and you had to
follow the wall
um and then suddenly you feel like okay
now there are other people also holding
the wall and you can you sort of feel
other people you go okay I need to stop
I don't I shouldn't follow the wall
anymore and at some point you're just
staring out in complete darkness the
space suddenly emerges your eyes adjust
to the very very low uh light uh well
the locks I don't know the exactly
illuminance I suppose in English
um the very low illuminance you start to
adjust and this can only happen over
time I think that this this sort of is
an example of temporality sensory
impression content uh I wouldn't say
call there because I don't buy into that
um I'm totally uh
I'm more of a Time person I don't know
if you get the impression
um but I have a question for you as well
Ellie if I may
because this this example that I just
gave here with with the James Terrell
and I'm an architect myself and usually
I give that example with the spaces
did you would you say that it's the same
experience or would you say that those
are two very different experiences
uh well certainly there are similarities
between those two experiences I'm not
sure if they're identical or even they
can be uh discussed in uh I don't know
in the same terms but
um going back to your
um point on the temporality and also
this skill the the discrepancy between
the diplomacy of the scale the Primacy
of the temporality as versus the scale
of time perception uh well I certainly
agree with you on that uh but I also
believe that you see uh
I don't think at least in my in my
opinion that the temporality or the
absolute flow or the at least you're
certainly an absolute flow is the most
fundamental
um
a fundamental concept that needs to be
grounded because uh there needs to be uh
even more fundamental prior to even
existence of that temporality or that
flow right uh which I'm not going into
details about how that fundamentality uh
can be accounted for or it can even be
discussed in terms of our observed
phenomena or our experience phenomena
but I wanted to thank both of you for
your
extensive response you provided and
helpful responses I wanted to
um
ask for your permission to uh I I wanted
to discuss these matters a bit further
with you so if you permit I wanted to
email you about them and discuss them a
bit further because that's something
that I'm deeply interested in so again
thank you so much
because Ali just mentioned this that he
doesn't think that the world is kind of
the basic thing and I I don't know to
what extent I agree but something I do
think that happens is that at least in
the Australian framework there's this
kind of conception that Consciousness or
subjectivity more generally is this kind
of layered or hierarchical structure of
which you have to find literally the
bases and go from the ground up so to
speak and I think there's something true
to that but it's not completely it's not
as hierarchical as we would put it
because once again this brings us back
to the concept this relationship between
up activity and temporality for me I
would say
app activity inform centrality and
temporality in forms of activity are
co-emergent but how can you affect it
because you have a body and then you
introduce embodiment into the picture
and you've introduced environment to the
picture you open up a lot of like it's
you open up the Pandora's Box almost so
maybe this whole idea of the most basic
stuff it's a bit of a red herring but I
also think there's something valuable
and fun would agree on this bit is that
temporality is it's very abstract it's
just a formal structure which underpins
all experience regardless of whether
it's the most basic structure or not
that's a different question and that's
all I want to say for now awesome all
right
we'll pause in time and move on
Dean
please where does this take you
well I'm like Ali a whole bunch of
places I'm not like Ali in the sense
that I do place a very high priority and
emphasis
on timing and perspectives
um that doesn't mean that Ali and I
don't get along fantastically we do it's
just that it's that different
perspective thing that I think gives
this whole topic of certain richness
I want to touch for a second on on
Zach's
uh
teasing out the word skills because I
think that's really really important
here I'm my background is sort of in the
Practical aspects of learning
um so I I tend to zoom out on not just
the particulars but the whole picture
and
I want to just say before I ask my
question is
I thought it was a fantastic compare
comparative analysis in your paper
and I thought your your presentation and
your sharings today were also very clear
in terms of being able to show
difference insane which I think only
comes about when
we account for the temporality not that
I'm not saying measure it but at least
have a certain appreciation of it so
here's my here's my thing
practicalities in other words the
actions and active inference
are not necessarily always a capture
that that could be one form of an action
but it's not the only one there's there
are plays there are creations and
compositions
which we looking at category Theory are
are quite intimately familiar with now
so
one of the things that I
tried to bring
to the conversation about a decade ago I
was working with a number of people in
complexity science and complexity
research and they were a huge match
Arana and Varela fans and for about two
years all I did was have conversations
like the one we're having today with
complexity scientists
and one of the things I tried to bring
to them in terms of understanding the
possibility of applying skills as
learning were
number one
you first have to be able to get people
to pay some sort of attention
have an awareness
of of what they are embedded in what
their Niche is what is being signaled to
them Etc
number two you have to be able to link
and combine and I know that in a lot of
formal learning settings that is that
that Association piece that skill of
being able to do that sort of compare
and is this same Is this different again
category Theory stuff there's a heavy
emphasis placed on that
then there's another skill which is
to be able to set a rule
to be able to scale up around what is
consistent what is seeming to be able to
have a certain shelf life
and things that are changing rapidly
because we you guys talked a lot about
change today so that's basically an
understanding you can you can know in
English where that came for me basically
standing under the abstracted state the
heuristics the little sort of rules of
thumb that you apply as a skill
subjectively
and then finally and this is one that's
left off of most
out of most conversations there's a
particular type of software and all of
these are self organizations even if
you're being prompted by the teacher you
still have to take up the skill of
organizing yourself
but there's a fourth type of skill which
is a particular type of
self-organization which is being the
capacity to transfer recapitulate in a
timely manner and I think that's where
your paper is opening up a bit of a
Pandora's Box it's not just a comparison
of objective and subjective time it's
how how do we know when to reapply the
rule
and I think from a learning standpoint
that's a
that's a big moment it's not just a
Eureka moment but it's a sense of
do my inferences
now withstand the scrutiny of the
environment the environment generally
not just the niche so is the niche
capturing us or are we still free to
think about how that next move
fits with all the prior moves and I
think that requires
the representation that you guys had in
your paper that essential diagonal line
and so
I think
I think that's what you did I think what
you've touched on it and put into into
defendable form is okay so there's
there's all these skills and do we cut
ourselves off at the at the at the more
phenomenological ones are you paying
attention are you making associations or
are you freeing yourself up to be able
to have these rules but then know when
to re-purpose them as the context
changes so I want to applaud you because
I I've had many many conversations for
over a decade where there's a whole
bunch of people who do not want to talk
about the third and the fourth skill
because it's hard to measure
but I think you guys have brought some
um
some ability to
compose that and so that's all I wanted
to say I don't have any questions just
want to give you a
two claps
thank you thank you very much that's
that's uh wow thanks thanks a lot the
I don't even know what to say because uh
I guess to Juan Diego and I
it was actually I think over a Twitter
conversation we sort of realized a few
things and basically
well linked up and started working on
this and apparently we have a lot in
common in terms of philosophy uh well
and also other things but
um interestingly we found out that there
was actually a you know plausible
retractable uh relationship that we
could exploit
um
so well uh thanks thanks a lot
I'm very happy to see that there's
someone else who is also like a very
temporal person right like think
thinking about things in time and and
events rather than things and I think
this is a very important distinction
yeah for sure thank you for that coming
Dean and I also think that it can kind
of speaks uh to the whole temporal thing
we're talking about precisely because
what we learned we learn through time
and that's kind of obvious but but you
have to kind of address how The
centrality Works in order to eventually
talk about learning and pulling rules
and being
understanding our environments you were
saying kind of understanding how to
apply these rules like how to apply
different skills in a proper environment
adaptively so to speak and something
that first uh kind of attracted me to
the active inference and fep context
possibly these possibility of making
sense of how through updates to genetic
models
um you can try to make sense formally of
the of these skills and this process
that underline what it's like to be you
know an organism and a human being you
know changing world and once again it
brings us back to change temporality all
this stuff it's all connected
I just can I just do one quick follow-up
Daniel because I know I want to make
sure you have some time as well I think
what people struggle with is they can
name it
and call it transference
and oftentimes that gets conflated with
understanding and wisdom and that isn't
necessarily so that timely way of being
able to recapitulate something is an
incredibly important skill if we get
that wrong we oftentimes you know
materially fall off a cliff
but whether or not we can see it as both
discretized as its own entity its own
particulars and part of this massive
whole that requires all of these priors
as well
being able to juggle that I think is
again
that's what you've opened up here and
hopefully
people are able to then take that
information and test it because that's
the best thing to do I in fact this
morning in a in another separate
conversation altogether
um I was asked how to take some of the
practicalities and the skills that you
guys talked about in your paper and
apply them in real real time and it's
not really really hard if you have at
least those four skills it is very
difficult if you stop at the associative
level or if you if you stop at the I
built a rule now and I know how far that
rule will extend
so that's my my final say for today go
ahead sorry Daniel
oh it's all it's all great
um so many threads
weaving together so again to to both
presenters and authors it was it was
excellent
um
the the dominant
uh sense or impression is is that it's
very evocative what you've presented the
idea of a generative passage not just as
a touch upon generative models
generative AI but also this idea that
our travels are generative like whenever
we see a friend and we take the train we
always have some story to share and like
something that happened along the way I
know that's not necessarily how it's
used but it's just what it evoked when
you describe formal dynamical models as
generative passages it's not 95 Theses
to pin onto the door it's something that
evokes and you even spoke about taking
different perspectives on your work
rather than your work advancing a
perspective and then to hear about the
connections with the um light and sound
art and visual art and uh the the notion
of architecture and your background Zach
and and the interplay between space and
time time and the way that sometimes we
can look at a blueprint and see it as
static or even the constructed embodied
building as a static object when it also
moves through time
um then one more impression and then a
question
finally the um the vocabulary and the
the delicacy of the articulation with
the protention retention and the Primal
impression or the living presence
and then the way in which graphically
you arranged it
um along orthogonal axes like rows and
columns that allowed us to slide through
on the diagonal
um it gives a lot to work with
and my question is where is the action
perception Loop or how do you believe
that this
time Consciousness and Associated
methods and skills
how can we then go back to potentially
earlier or contemporary representations
of the particular partition under the
fep or just the active uh inference
action perception Loop
how can we see that or be with that
differently with the advances that are
happening literally in the last year in
this area
oh man that's
right on I mean spot on this this is
exactly the kind of research I do
basically
um I have like I guess two paths in my
research
um I think eighty percent of my time is
Empirical research doing Neuroscience uh
and basically doing experiments all the
time and one way that I translate all of
this all of these insights that I get
from from working with someone like Juan
Diego is to try to understand them as uh
what I what I like to think about as a
sensory motor entropy uh basically
talking about it as the interaction and
the loop that naturally occurs not only
in actual perception but also in past
and present and if I may just briefly
um share my screen again I would like to
show you that
um this last aspect I think I hope you
can see my arrow I'm not sure
um I'm just gonna take the laser pointer
just to be sure that this last Point
here I think this sort of maybe over
here is better you can see that the
retention and the pro tension sort of uh
correlating or sort of you know um
meeting here in the middle and sort of
creating a loop through time so if we
have to jump from this point this is the
update step some from updates that one
to two you sort of need to create this
interwoven link between them this is
naturally creating a loop between uh
well action and perception because
actions breaks you what brings you
forward in time perception was part of
the retention and basically there will
be this naturally occurring Loop just
from basic principles of temporality
it's like you cannot get around that
action perception sort of emerges from
from temporality all naturally
um so in my opinion the way that I think
about it is as sensory motor entropy and
basically you can look at that and the
amazing results that people are finding
now around the thalamus which is
basically the essential organ of the
brain the subcortical structure actually
functions as a bridge between major
brain regions right so for you to
actually perform any kind of action it
needs to use the thalamus as a bridge
which means that it's in intrinsically
related to the way things change and
there's like this I guess you can think
about it not as things but as events
right so to give an example like Juan
Diego did with his uh this is my cup and
the fact that my car continuously exists
is not the thing that exists uh all the
time but there are events occurring in
which this one continues to exist right
so it's more about thinking of the
evolution of time being highly
correlated with itself rather than
thinking about things existing in time
but this is like a reverse way of
thinking about it and the typical
strategy of of active inferences
clipping things on the head and see if
it actually still makes sense in this
case I I genuinely think it does I don't
know if I if I answered your question
yes thank you Dean
yeah I would I would hold just to be
able to hold up two things again I would
say that there is the bridging piece and
there is also the high occupancy vehicle
Lane as opposed to the intersection like
a lot of the ways that we represent this
stuff is when we get those X and Y
um vectors Crossing one another but
there's also uh let's get all four
skills into one onto one platform and
remove a lot of the impediments and
that's that flipping part I I would
agree exactly with what you're saying
you have to have both
one as a metaphor as a metaphor it's all
that's all it is metaphorical but if you
can get all four skills in one place
and then down down the distance you'll
shorten the amount of time it takes to
arrive at wherever you're going
thank you
one
um and please feel free to give kind of
your your your closing thoughts and next
angles as we come near I don't even know
whether to call it an ends
so I just wanted to
to to Daniel's question because I
thought was a great question one I
didn't think about at least in the
specific terms with Zach we've
discussing precisely kind of the the
where action fits in all the story and
this of course brings us to the action
perception Loop and I guess I'm going to
do what we usually do in our
collaborations with Sac which is I'll
bring the phenomenology and see whether
it fits and and I think it fits quite
well because what we did in our model is
to show that there's precisely this
boundary portal boundary to the to the
updating scheme of active inference
which integrates pattern future but we
and we kind of relate this to protection
rate tension Primal attraction and you
have this nice living present what is
fascinating is that when you go a step
further away from the pure temporal form
of experience you have an embodied being
whose anticipations whose protections
are not some not simply the tones are
coming from the melody but what do you
do with them or what do you do so if I
see my bottle again this bottle appears
as something I can grasp and you can
think about this in terms of importances
action possibilities it's in that very
clear in the phenomenological literature
and also I think in the active influence
literature when we talk about action
policies and you know specific
importances all this stuff
and it is fascinating because then you
get action just by introducing the
temporal aspect of of active inference
but this action is always informed by
prior observation so by literally
perception and that happens well in
phenomenology all our actions are
important but what we are seeing what
we're perceiving more generally and what
what we've perceived in the past and you
can just kind of unfold that Loop and
get a very nice correlation between
action and perception through time so
the actual perception look is not like
this monolithic Circle it's something
that it's more like a spiral so to speak
and I think our model speaks to that
anything to this
it really would make uh worlds of
difference to call it an action
perception spiral if it's just gonna be
a visual metaphor and rely on our
cultural understandings of shapes
why not firstly hold up multiple and
then secondly bring in
um this kind of
perhaps even double helical or triple
helical nature of of unfolding and three
makes a party
so
it's awesome
um
Ollie and Dean first any closing
um thoughts and then the the authors
with the final words
I'll be really quick I really want to
thank you both for uh sharing the paper
and uh the great presentation
thank you Dean Ali
yeah as I said it was a really
fascinating paper for me personally
because uh I was really obsessed with
um process thinking processual and all
kinds of dynamic thinking so again I
really wanted to thank you for writing
such an amazing paper uh yeah thank you
so much
awesome and so to the authors
um
any closing thoughts or where you'll be
heading now or what you're excited what
you're pretending
I guess first of all I would just like
to thank you because it's been an
amazing experience an experience simple
experience actually just to discuss our
paper with you thank you for reading the
paper thank you for enjoying the paper
and happiness it's it's been lovely and
uh I I think it's quite clear that the
way to go now is to start talking about
action and see how it fits and hopefully
sooner right until later you'll see
something about this because it's
probably what we're discussing with Zach
more recently
yeah I also would like to extend this
thank you uh it's fantastic to just I
mean the whole active inference
Institute is just in my opinion the
right thing uh it's really amazing to to
follow
um so I'm very happy to to be part of
this
um Beyond uh well besides the the active
aspect of uh hopefully the next paper uh
I'm also looking into phases and looking
at active inference as if it did not
work with States because I think that's
too spatial and it's making things
static but actually moving that into
phases into a continuous space
um is something that I'm trying to
establish now uh
trying to start up a collaboration with
Ryan Smith about that but it's still a
really early work in progress so
hopefully we'll see something from that
project in a few months time hopefully
but but thanks again thank you
awesome thank you all for joining thanks
everybody for listening and you're
always welcome back so till the next
time
bye thank you